Fanggui Li Collection 1928-1982 Mss.Ms.Coll.119
American Philosophical Society
Fanggui Li Collection
1928-1982
Mss.Ms.Coll.119
American Philosophical Society
1.5 Linear feet
As s student of Edward Sapir at the University of Chicago, Fanggui (Fang-Kuei) Li spent two months during the summer of 1928 in northern Alberta studying Chipewyan and went on to a career that included pioneering work in other Athapascan languages, Tai, and Chinese. A lontime member of the Academia Sinica, Li was for many years a professor of Linguistics at the University of Washington and, at the end of his career, at the University of Hawaii. The Li Collection is comprised of ten volumes containing stories in Chipewyan collected in northern Alberta in 1928 by the Chinese-American linguist, Fanggui Li, along with an extensive Chipewyan slip file. The texts contain phonetic transcriptions of stories elicited from François Mandeville and Baptiste Ferrier with interlinear English translations. These were edited and published Fanggui as Li and Ronald Scollon, Chipewyan Texts (Taipei: Academia Sinica, 1976). The collection also includes two cassettes containing an oral history interview with Li conducted in November 1982 by M. Terry Thompson and Laurence Thompson.
Li, Fanggui
Bibliography
Li, Fanggui and Ronald Scollon, Chipewyan Texts (Taipei: Academia Sinica, 1976). [Based principally upon the Chipewyan texts of François Mandeville]
Scollon, Ronald, Linguistic Convergence: an Ethnography of Speaking at Fort Chipewyan (N.Y.: Academic Press, 1979). [Includes important biographical information on Li and the context of the 1928 field season]
Scollon, Ron and Suzanne Wong Scollon. "Fang Kuei Li (1902-1987), an obituary" American Anthropologist 91 (1989):1008-1009.
Related Archival Materials note
Li, Fanggui, Mattole, An Athabaskan Language (Chicago: Univ,. of Chicago, 1930). Call no.: 497.3 L622m
Additional correspondence of Fanggui Li is located in the papers of Franz Boas (B B61, including a two page report of the field season of 1928) and in the correspondence of the American Council of Learned Societies Committee on Native American Languages (506.73 Am72co). The latter collection contains a report of his 1927 fieldwork with Sapir on Hupa, Mattole, and Wailaki, and correspondence relating to his grant.
Separated Materials note
One book owned by Li has been transferred for storage to the Printed Materials Department:
LeGoff, Laurent, Grammaire de la Langue Montagnaise (Montreal, 1889).
Two audio recordings of an oral history interview conducted by Laurence C. Thompson, 1982, have been transferred for storage with the Audiovisual materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated to the APS by M. Terry and Laurence Thompson, March 30, 1996 (1996-251, 252ms, 253r.
Scope and Contents note
The heart of the Fanggui Li Collection is comprised of ten notebooks kept by the Chinese-American linguist Fanggui Li relating to his research on the Chipewyan language in 1928. Recorded in the field, these texts consist of phonetic transcriptions of stories elicited from François Mandeville in Chipewyan (and, in one instance, Baptiste Ferrier) in July 1928, with interlinear English translations.
The balance of the collection consists of an extensive slipfile for the Chipewyan language, and two audio cassettes of oral history interviews conducted by Laurence C. Thompson and M. Terry Thompson in 1982, concering Li's memories of Edward Sapir and other colleagues in linguistics.
Biographical/Historical note
A student of Edward Sapir at the Univerity of Chicago, the linguist Fanggui (Fang-Kuei) Li was a pioneer in studying the Canadian and Pacific Coast Athapascan languages. After completing a Master's thesis on the Sarcee verb-stem in 1927, Li was advised by Sapir to continue on to other Athapascan languages, and with funding provided in part by the American Council of Learned Societies Committee on Native American Languages, he spent the summer of 1927 getting an introduction to field research by working under Sapir on the Hupa reservation in California. Much of Li's effort that summer was spent on the language of the coastal Mattole, which had received virtually no previous attention, and to a lesser degree on Wailaki.
In the following year, Li arranged for two months of fieldwork at Fort Chipewyan, Alberta, where he studied the Chipewyan language with François Mandeville, a "half-breed from Fort Resolution." Arriving on June 28, 1928, Li worked intensively with Mandeville, whom he considered "very intelligent," although his dialect differed from that recorded by Père LeGoff in his Grammaire de la Langue Montagnaise (Montreal, 1889). Li had selected Chipewyan on the belief that it contained more "archaic features" than other Athapascan languages, and believed that it would therefore provide insight into the linguistic evolution of the family. During this field trip, he also collected material on Hare at Fort Smith and some Slavey. Later in his career, he did important work on determining the relationships between Eyak and other Athapascan languages.
Although Li retained an interest in Athapascan languages, by 1937 he became almost completely absorbed in classifying the major languages and dialects of China, the work for which he is best remembered. Li reconginized seven major branches, Mandarin (or Northern), Wu, Xiang, Gan, Kejia (or Hakka), Yue (or Cantonese), and Min.
Associated with the Institute of History and Philology from the 1920s on, Li held appointments in the Departments of Linguistics and Anthropology at the University of Washington until the 1970s, moving to the University of Hawaii.
Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939; Thompson, Laurence C.; Thompson, M. Terry; Chipewyan language; Field notes.; Indians of North America--Languages; Linguistics; Slip files
- Fanggui Li Collection, 1928-1982; 1.5 lin. feet
  - Chipewyan Texts I, July 1928; 60p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes stories and interlinear translations elicited from François Mandeville:
    How the Indian children were taught (p.1)
    Fishing (p.24)
    How copper was first found (p.37, cont. in next vol.)
  - Chipewyan Texts II, July 1928; 60p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
    How iron was first found (p.16)
    How dà ts á í lived (p.28, cont. in next vol.)
  - Chipewyan Texts III, July 1928; 60p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
    Includes stories and interlinear translations elicited from Baptiste Ferrier and (second) François Mandeville:
    The story of bèts ú é yè nét cà (p.1)
    How dà ts á í lived (p.8, cont. from prev. vol.)
    Untitled (p.19)
    Untitled (p.51)
  - Chipewyan Texts IV, July 1928; 60p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
    Untitled (p.1, cont. from vol. III)
    Untitled (p.7)
    The story of túrì (p.16)
  - Chipewyan Texts V, July 1928; 60p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
    The story of Oà tOè tì (p.1)
    Untitled (p.37, cont. in next vol.)
  - Chipewyan Texts VI, July 1928; 49p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
    Untitled (p.1, cont. from prev. vol.)
    The story of the man-eater (p.9)
    The story of a man who has slept with a bear (p.28)
    The adventures of Beaulieu (p.45)
  - Chipewyan Texts VII, July 1928; 58p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
  - Chipewyan Texts VIII, July 1928; 50p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
    The story of a man who became a wolf (p.17)
  - Chipewyan Texts IX, July 1928; 73p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
    The man who cheated in gambling (p.11)
    The last Dogribs who ran in flight (p.19)
    How I made a canoe (p.25)
    How moose hide is tanned (p.33)
    The prophet of the Yellow-Knives (p.41)
    My Beaver Hunt (p.54)
  - Chipewyan Texts X, July 1928; 32p.; Li, Fanggui (Box 1)
    Includes stories and interlinear translations elicited from François Mandeville(?):
    The story of a wise man, 1 (p.5)
    The story of a wise man, 2 (p.19)
  - Chipewyan Slipfile, [1928]; 1 lin. foot (ca.1,500 slips); Li, Fanggui (Box 2)
  - Reminiscences of Edward Sapir and others, November 22, 1982; 2.0 Tape(s) 2 audiocassettes; Thompson, Laurence C. and M. Terry Thompson